My sons, 5th and 7th graders, fight a lot.
(Questioner) I am a mother of two sons:
5th and 7th graders.
From early days of our marriage,
my husband and I used to fight a lot.
After a few years of listening
to your teachings,
our relationship has improved
and we get along well now.
Now, my sons fight over trivial things.
My older son often curses at
and sometimes hits his younger brother.
The younger one disrespects
and talks back to his older brother.
Or he ignores what his older brother says.
Yesterday, when it became his older
brother's turn to play the computer game,
the younger one didn't give up
the seat so they fought fiercely
They hit and scratched each other,
even threw a chair and got it broken.
I used to intervene
in the past but yesterday,
I just stayed out and
let them resolve their conflicts.
But I felt very distressed
and felt sorry for my sons.
I was reminded of our fights
over little things in the past.
I imagine they will continue to fight.
Whenever I see them fight, I get
distressed and don't know what to do.
I would like to know when I can intervene.
Yes. When this happens, you should go to
your room and do the prostration practice.
(Sunim) As you see them fighting,
(Sunim) "Gosh! There is no error
in Buddha's teachings."
"How could your words be so correct?'
"There is no way to avoid karma; this is
how karma returns, one after another."
"Oh, Thank you dear Buddha!" With these
thoughts, you must do the prostrations.
You have sowed the seeds,
so now you're reaping them, no?
(Questioner) Yes.
Your children witnessed you and
your husband's fight over trivial things,
so they have learned do the same.
You reap what you sow.
Don't' worry about
whether one is right or wrong.
"Ah, this is
how the cause and effect work!
It is clearly
the result of what I showed them."
You must learn from this.
(Questioner) Yes.
I can see that now.
(Questioner) I am reminded of our old day
when we used to fight.
I realize that the children must
have suffered when we were fighting.
I can see how their young minds must
have been hurt. I atone realizing this.
But when they're fighting
over really trivial things,
I feel that I may need to intervene.
Don't intervene, Let them be.
Remember that you
even as an adult and a mother,
you fought
over trivial things tooth and nail.
Right?
How could your children know
not to fight over trivial things?
Even if they fight ten times
more than you did,
you ought to understand them
as immature children and leave them alone.
And when you harvest what you sowed,
you don't reap one plant per seed, right?
(Questioner) Yes.
One seed can sprout 10-20 plants.
Though I planted one seed
but the yield can be much more.
So, understand what I said before,
you should thank Buddha while prostrating.
"You can't escape karma;
the law of causality is truly clear."
You need to do this prayer of repentance.
Don't intervene.
You and your husband,
after learning Buddha's teachings,
have repented and now live well, right?
(Questioner) Yes.
Your children will also learn,
repent and live well someday,
if you don't intervene
and only do your praying diligently
(Questioner) But I am worried
about one thing.
(Questioner) The older one is
big and strong
(Questioner) while the younger one is
rather thin and small.
When the older one hits
or pushes the younger one,
he falls over easily.
So, I worry that he will get hurt.
I worry that he may endure
some serious damage.
That's OK. You are not damaged
by your husband who is bigger than you.
Right? (Audience laughter)
It's OK. (Questioner laughter)
When the little one disrespects the older
one,he ought to get beaten up a bit.
So that the younger one will learn
not to disrespect his older brother.
And, the older one can realize that
he could go to jail
if he damages his younger brother.
If he beats up someone outside,
he could land in jail.
But within the house, he can learn to
repent and work things out.
If you didn't' get broken bones
by beating, so your kid will be OK.
(Questioner) Yes, thank you.
(Applause)
Of course, you worry as a mother
when you see your kids fighting.
When I say these things,
you folks may think:
"Well, since you as a monk with no kids,
can say such heartless things."
"How can a mother just sit back and watch?"
You may think this way.
But, it's OK.
Because kids grow up
in the midst of this sort of things.
But if it becomes a real problem,
they learned it from whom?
Who gave birth to them?
Who raised them?
They take after whom?
They could not have learned it
from anywhere else.
They have learned everything from you.
So when these things occur,
you can see the law of causality
and retribution clearly.
You can see that Buddha shows
you clearly the law of causality.
So, if you don't want this sort of result,
you should not create the cause.
If I want certain kind of result,
I should create the related causes.
You can see this
as an occasion to learn such law.
Instead of interfering with then, if you
want good results, what do you need to do?
You do good deeds.
If you don't want the punishment?
Avoid doing bad deeds.
How wonderful it is to see
clearly the law of causality works!
People don't realize that
if you sow in the spring,
you will have to reap in the fall.
You don't see the seed you planted
but when autumn comes,
you can see the crops all over the place
where you planted the seeds.
So, by observing you children
you can consider that
you are doing
your life study through them.
Your children are fighting
in order to wake you up.
Through their fighting
you can see you own self.
You raised your children
in a household of fighting.
If your children were good, you would not
know the law of causality and retribution.
Right? As an old saying goes,
with great suffering,
like getting your tongue pulled
out a foot, you would wake up.
Make this an opportunity for you to
wake up and avoid living a foolish life.
Don't worry too much about
the kids' fighting.